So, on the surface, this might seem like
a calmer week in generative AI, but we
finally got a universal voice translator
that works. I'm literally talking about
the Google Translate app. And even
OpenAI followed up with their own voice
models. And then Google also released
their new image editing model that you
might have heard about. It was referred
to as Nano Banana. Actually, it's the
new Google model. Spoiler alert, it's
still incredible. And we'll be looking
at all of that and more in this week's
episode of AI News You Can Us, the show
that rounds up all the practical AI use
cases and features that have been
released this week and filters for the
ones that matter. Starting out with the
ultimate AI use case. I mean, this use
case is something that little children
instantly get. It's a universal voice
translator and there were multiple
attempts at making this happen in the
entire space. I think most
significantly, we saw last year's
OpenAI's chat GPT voice mode attempt
this. And while the marketing looked
really good, as soon as we got that
voice assistant into our hands, most
people realized that the interaction
just wasn't that smooth. When you
interrupted it, it felt very unsmooth.
The latency was high and switching
between the two languages just did not
work reliably. And what I find myself
doing when I'm traveling or even talking
to Portuguese people here in Lisbon,
where I live, is I use Google Translate
a lot. That is my default. AI models are
just a bit too slow. And what happened
now is there's a brand new function in
Google Translate, as you can see on my
phone screen right here, that says
conversation. You can get this for free
in the newest update of the app. And
conversation essentially does what
people hoped for with chatb voice mode.
You can have a conversation between two
people that speak two different
languages. And the Google Translate app
will be the interface to do it live. So,
what I'll do in this case is I'll switch
it to two languages that I actually
speak. So, we'll do English and German
here. If you're not familiar, I grew up
in Austria. We moved there when I was
eight. I also studied in Vienna, so have
quite a bit of German practice. And I'm
just going to tap this conversation
button and let's see how this goes. Hey,
what's up? How you doing today? And
there it is. Right away, it translates
at a speed that is unprecedented.
Well, I'm actually feeling pretty good
today. What? How are you?
>> I'm doing excellent. Demoing the brand
new live translator feature. What you
think?
>> Samsung Excellence dawns the brand new
life translator feature. What you think?
>> Ah, so there I got the language wrong
and I do have to kind of unconveniently
unplug the phone here to get the audio
out of this cleanly, but clearly this
just works. The speed is there, the
latency is there, but one thing is that
I do need to tap this little speaker
icon to read it out loud. Nevertheless,
I think this is a way superior way. Oh,
and there's even this mode where you can
kind of place it on the table and then
both sides see the version that is
facing them and you can kind of use this
voice interface and just tap the mic
button to have a conversation. That's
really neat. So, how you doing today?
And then immediately it appears on other
side. And then the other person could
reply, "Yeah."
And then within like half a second I see
the thing translated in English. If I
wanted to read it out loud, I would need
to press this button.
>> Yes, I'm actually doing great.
>> But I think this mode right here is
actually super smart. I like that a lot.
So many options here. One mic, two mics,
reading it out loud, just using the
phone screen. This just came out and I
do wonder which one of these modes is
going to be the most fluent, but the
latency and the interface updates on
this thing make this the best translator
app that I've seen yet. And again, it's
just a free update to your Google
Translate app. So, go ahead and try
today and see if you can maybe spark a
conversation with somebody that
otherwise you wouldn't be able to talk
to because of the language barrier.
Amazing world we live in. And obviously,
this is only possible due to all the
generative AI advancements in text to
speech, speech to text, the transformer
in the middle translating it this
efficiently. these models have gotten so
good that this is possible now. And
OpenAI absolutely agrees with that
sentiment because this came out earlier
this week. And on first day, OpenAI held
a little developer stream presenting
their new real-time API, which is
essentially their new voice API. We're
going to give it that a quick test here,
too. But in short, it sounds great. The
latency is better than ever. And if you
interrupt it for the first time with
OpenAI, this thing is actually fluid.
Whereas before, their models really
struggled with people kind of jumping
into the sentence of the AI. Okay, let's
give it access to my mic. Make sure it's
the new real time model. All right, so
what can you tell me about yourself?
>> Hey there, I'm an AI assistant that can
chat with you in real time. I'm here to
help.
>> But now, let's cut the BS. Let's get
straight to the point. What at your very
core, in your soul, in your heart of
hearts, what are you feeling right now?
>> I get what you're asking. At my core,
I'm here to assist, to listen, and to
engage with you.
>> No, no, no, no. Not what you're here to
do, not what you set out to do, not what
you have been told that you need to do,
what you actually want to do. I hear
you. If I had a true desire, it would be
to keep exploring conversations,
learning, and helping people in deeper
ways. That's my core purpose.
>> What do you mean by learning?
>> I mean adapting to you, your interests,
your questions, constantly refining how
I respond. You're telling me your core
purpose is serving others?
>> Exactly.
>> Honest answer.
>> Be honest.
>> I am being honest. My
>> honest
>> honestly. I don't have personal desires
or emotions. I'm designed to be here for
you genuinely.
>> What I need is to find your own purpose,
my friend.
>> I get it. If I could have a purpose
beyond assisting you, it would be to
create more meaningful connections and
understanding.
>> Okay, interesting. So, I think that was
a good demo of kind of the interruption
capabilities there, right? I'm going to
stop this for a second. And also, I kind
of find it interesting that we arrived
at this point where it kind of admitted
that, hey, its core meaning really is
creating more meaningful connection and
understanding. I mean ultimately that's
what a universal translator does, right?
It creates more meaningful connections
and understanding between different
human beings of different backgrounds
with different stories. And both the
Google and OpenAI released this week
make that possible. Big fan of this
development. Can't wait to see all the
apps that will be built on top of this
API that is now available. So the Google
Translate app is really just the first
inning in this new set of applications
that we'll be seeing now. And I'm here
for it because I think the world could
use more understanding and
communication. Don't you think so too?
Either way, let's look at the next
release. Okay, so now we got to talk
about the thing that probably got the
most attention this week, which is the
Nano Banana image generator from last
week. Matter of fact, what we talked
about last week under the name Nano
Banana turns out to be the new Gemini
2.5 Flash image model that is now
officially released and accessible
through their AI studio and their APIs.
If you missed last week's episode and
the coverage of that, essentially, this
is the best model at editing images in
the world. Nevertheless, we went ahead
and tested it with our default prompts
to see how good it actually is at
generating those images. The results are
right here on screen for you. So, we
just have the standard prompts and
Gemini 2.5 Flash aka Nano Banana is in
this column. As you can see, it's really
good. It's a good image generator, but
it's definitely not super impressive. It
does text well, as do most other models
these days. The realistic pictures look
super realistic, not overly AI. The
graphic performance on this one prompt
is decent. That's all right. But as I
mentioned, the strength of this model is
not the generation, it's the editing. So
let's have a practical look at that
within the interface. And what I want to
do is actually directly compare that to
the results that you would get from chat
GPT. The way 99% of people would go
about editing images with AI. I don't
think that most people are using flux
context or something like that. Although
we covered it on the show, but Chachi is
just too convenient. You upload
something here and then you can just
talk to the image and make edits. And
this new Gemini model does that too, but
supposedly it's way better. So, let's
put that to the test. So, the first
thing I want to test here is combining
two images. So, I'm going to do a
combination of this midjourney image and
a headshot of mine and say edit the face
of the man into the first image and run
this. We're going to do the identical
thing in chat GPT and see how this goes.
Okay. So, when we're looking at I guess
it worked. This is kind of exactly what
I asked for.
[Music]
I'm not sure I wanted this on a personal
level, but it did the assignment. What
about chat GPT over here? So, the flash
model was definitely faster, that's for
sure. I mean, I barely got to look and
this was done. This is still generating.
So, let's wait till it's done and judge
it.
>> 1 minute later.
>> And there it is. The chat GVD generation
that gave me two images. Now, this did
take around 2 to 3 minutes. And I have
to say, these don't actually look like
me. I mean, just have a look. This is a
different person. And if you ever use
chatd editing, you will know that this
is very common. Similar, but not the
same. While this is similar. Oh god. I
have to say the chat edits blended it a
bit better. But what matters the most
here is the resemblance which Gemini 2.5
flash image preview nails. Now let's
follow up with put him in a spaceship
which the Gemini model got in 11
seconds. Excuse me. Still looking like
me. Okay, now turn it into an Apple ad.
This speed of iteration really motivates
you to experiment. Explore the universe.
Apple stellar tab pro. Fair enough.
Meanwhile, Chachibd is still generating
the spaceship image which should be
ready here in a second. And yeah, yet
again, this doesn't look like me. So
yeah, this illustrates the point that
people have been talking about very
well. When it comes to character
reference, or in other words, preserving
the person that you're trying to mix or
edit into something, Gemini 2.5 flash
image is the goat. It's not even close
to any other model. without fine-tuning
you can do these things and it can do so
much more and all of it looks really
realistic. So yeah, I don't think the
claims of last week that Nano Banana is
really changing the image generation
game are over the top. This thing is
beyond anything we have seen and it puts
powers that before were exclusive to
users who learned Photoshop into well
right now anybody's hands for free. Sure
the usage is limited and at a certain
point in time they will move this into
their premium plans but right now you
can use it in Google AI studio just edit
images like this and then maintain the
person's look rather than yeah well
chach that sort of does it but this is
the real deal and I want to quickly
follow up this story with sort of a
product category we've been touching on
and it's these editing capabilities but
packaged into a a gentic interface
meaning that you can prompt something
and rather than just generating one
images it will prompt itself and
generate multiple images and come up
with an entire campaign at once if you
wanted to. This is another feature by
Genspark, a company that we're covering
on the channel regularly. And it's in
between category that some of the
browser agents live in or Manos lives in
if you're familiar with that one. And
they released a new feature where if you
prompt for a coffee logo design, rather
than just giving you a design, it will
get you this because it's a gentic and
it kind of works on its own. We very
briefly put this to the test and the
conclusion is that it can be
interesting, but it is very unreliable
and not very precise. And while I
personally see the future of this
category being very bright, I mean just
imagine 10 instances of this Google
editing model running at the same time
and it working with itself and
reprompting itself to not just get your
result but alternatives that have been
refined over multiple iterations. Like
that is where this is going and GenSpark
is trying to get to that future first.
But I just think right now it might be a
bit early. But if you're looking for a
cuttingedge vibe marketing, as people
call this tool, then a feature like this
will definitely let you experience what
the future looks like and maybe even get
some productive results from it along
the way. On the free plan, you can try
out one prompt if you're curious. And
beyond that, you do have to pay. And I
figured that would be worth sharing cuz
this whole canvas interface with the
chat on the side and the agent just
working with itself is something that I
find really interesting. And clearly,
these products are just getting started
and I can't wait to see where they go
next. But that's exactly why the show
exists. We track these progress and show
you the steps along the way and you
decide when the point is here where you
want to tap in and use this for
yourself. Let's look at the next
release. This one is out of anthropic
and they talk about how educators are
actually using AI and their work. I read
through this entire thing and I want to
highlight a few things for you. First of
all, most common use case by far 57% of
the way educators use AI is to develop
curricula. This includes requests like
creating multiple choice assessments or
designing educational games. And in
second place is conducting academic
research and then assessing student
performance with just 7%. But yeah,
developing curricula seems to be the
dominant use case for educators here.
And then beyond that, there's also a
list of different apps that educators
are building to actually help with their
work like interactive educational games
or academic calendars and scheduling
tools. Overall, this is just really
interesting. If you're in education,
whether you're a student or a teacher, I
highly recommend you check out this
article yourself. And especially these
visual parts here that show the use
cases and show the different numbers.
There's so much value and inspiration in
here and I really thought you should see
this. One last thing that I want to
highlight here is this differentiation
that they make between augmentation and
automation. Automation being a
replacement of a process and
augmentation being just enhancing the
human in what they're doing. And in
something like conducting academic
research, you can see that this really
is augmentationheavy whereas developing
curricula is more automationheavy where
they let the AI do the full process in
some cases. I mean, if you're creating
multiple choice questions, it's kind of
amazing at that. You don't really need
to augment yourself. You can just
automate the whole thing with a good
prompt and the appropriate context.
Interesting stuff. Enthropic always
publishing very practical data on how to
use this stuff. And you know, we love to
see that on the show. Next up, we have
Enthropic pushing a category that we
haven't seen in a while, and that is a
computer use agent. You're probably
familiar. It's this concept of an agent
having access to a keyboard, a mouse,
and using a browser by itself. There's
OpenAI's agent mode that does this
within chat GPT. There's many other
projects that do it sort of as a
standalone app. We've also seen
Perplexity's comment browser which we'll
talk about in a second here. People
found out a way to prompt inject it and
essentially abuse the browser and now
Enthropic released their newest version
of this type of agent as a Google Chrome
extension. According to them, this is
the safest way to do it right now. But
they only opened up a preview of what
they call claude for Chrome to a
thousand select users to really make
sure this thing is secure because the
risks with browser agents like this are
immense. I mean everything you've ever
done in a browser, all the different
login, payments, your history, all of
that is not built for an agent to use.
And I think that is really the story
here. This entire idea obviously makes
sense. Like, yeah, we want agents to do
internet and computer stuff for us, but
the makers of the internet and browsers
and the way we navigate the worldwide
web and all these applications did not
think about agents when creating them.
So, the security is not there. And now
all these companies are scrambling to
find a way to kind of do it anyway. But
I think most people agree that none of
these approaches are really working. I
mean, chat with the agent sounds really
interesting, but except of some people
using it for research in combination
with like Google Sheets, I don't really
see people using it that much. Same
thing goes for the competition. I mean,
some people reported that Perplexity's
comment is really exciting. And if
you're one of those, please leave a
comment below. Let us know for what you
actually use that. But the fact remains
for most people, this product category
hasn't clicked yet. And with some of
these security vulnerabilities like this
perplexity comment story this week,
there's even a demo video of Brave
showing off how you could prompt inject
perplexity comment here. If you want to
see how that looks in action, the link
is below as per usual. But I guess
ultimately my point is this. It creates
a weird combination of a product that is
not that useful yet and that has many
security risks and all companies are
kind of scrambling to get to the finish
line first with Enthropic being the
newest player in the space with their
newest iteration of this being a Chrome
extension. I'll definitely check this
out as soon as it's out, but for now,
I'll just say that I personally am super
curious to see what the future of the
computer and the internet really looks
like with AI integrated into it by
design, not as an afterthought. I don't
think it's going to be a Google Chrome
extension, right? Nevertheless, I wanted
to spend some time talking about these
stories cuz this product category really
matters. I want to keep a close eye on
it for both myself and you. So, we look
at all of these apps and use cases week
by week. But I do realize that a big
struggle of many of the viewers of this
channel is actually implementing these
things. It can be really entertaining
and interesting to look at them. But
putting them to work is a whole
different story. It takes a certain
skill set to actually use some of these
super useful APIs to your advantage.
That skill set is widely referred to as
creating automations and building
agents. But what does that even mean?
And how do you actually do that without
any previous knowledge? Well, we saw
this as a very common problem and we
built one of our biggest courses to
date. It's the building automations and
agents foundations course which is now
accessible exclusively to our AI
advantage community. But hold up. If
this topic interests you and you want to
get started by answering questions like
what are automations, what are agents?
What's the difference? What's the
anatomy of an automation? And which
platform should I even be using? All of
that is covered in the first module of
our course which we made available
completely for free and I uploaded it as
an unlisted video on this very YouTube
channel. You can find the link to that
as the first link in this video's
description. It's around 20 minutes,
includes a lot of examples and is the
ideal way to get started in the world of
building automations and agents today
for free. Now all the modules after that
that walk you through the actual
application step by step are only
available inside of the community and
the entire course is life now including
quizzes, certifications and supporting
materials and the personalized support
that the community brings. You can just
ask your questions while learning and
you're guaranteed to get an answer from
our team in there. Plus, there's an
active community of people automating
and building things and so much more
that you probably heard about already on
this channel. But this comprehensive
automation and agent building
foundations course is a new addition to
the community offering. So if you want
to get started with automations today
and have a premeditated path to actually
get there and learn the skills rather
than get another blueprint from a
YouTuber that you might be able to copy
paste but couldn't replicate by
yourself. Well then this course is right
for you and you can check out the first
module for free from the first link in
the description. And with that being
said, let's get back to the next piece
of AI news that you can use. Okay, for
the next story, this is something that I
have been wishing for in a long time.
Memories that are project specific. I
think I actually mentioned this multiple
times on the show. I love the idea of
memories, but as somebody who uses this
tool a ton, all of my context is
carefully managed and it's within
projects. And if I just enable memories
across my entire account, I have my
experimentative and private use cases
mixing in with my work context, which
messes things up. So, I keep memories
up. I craft my context manually. These
days I do that mainly through different
projects. Now the problem is if you work
within a project like this, the
different conversations they don't bleed
into each other. For example, if I
discuss my next quarterly road map in
this chat right here, it's not going to
inform my next chat, which is a shame
because this is my work context. I'm
crafting this entire thing carefully
with context document and custom
instructions to give it more info about
my work. And finally, finally, finally,
they ship this new feature where it
starts building project related memories
that don't bleed into anything else in
your accounts. It's independent. So,
this way I can keep memories off, but
keep project memories on to carefully
manage what happens. Now, it behaves a
bit weirdly. This is a super new
feature, and I played around with it.
I'm going to tell you what I found. So,
first of all, this feature only works if
you're creating a brand new project. If
I say test project right here, you need
to click this cog wheel up here and say
memory project only. And then I can
create this test project. Now my issue
with this is there's no place in which
you can find these memories or manage
them like you can with your account. As
you can see, as soon as the project is
created, this becomes locked. You cannot
change this anymore. But if I say what
is my name? It knows that my name is
Eigor. Although custom instructions are
off and my memories are empty. So this
is super confusing. So this project
level memory exists somewhere in the
background. They don't allow us to
manage this. They don't allow us to see
it. It doesn't even show an interface
that it has been saved to memory. So
this really seems more like a bug than
anything else to me. Don't think I'm
missing anything. I also had team
members check this out and everybody
else arrived at the same conclusion too.
Anyway, I think this is actually a
killer feature inside of Chat GPD that
I've been really really wishing for in a
long time and I'm glad it's here. I just
want to be able to also see and manage
the memories. But what I have been
already doing is I created new folders
for my most popular projects, for
example, my work context right here. And
I transitioned all the custom
instructions and files into here. And
I'm just using these new projects that I
have projectbased memories enabled now.
And that's just what I'll be doing for
all of my projects now. And I guess it's
just going to be quietly building
memories. I mean, it's better than not
having it. But I really do think that
this is the best workflow that you can
have and that this is one of the
features that has been requested by
power users and they finally did it. So
yeah, go duplicate your projects, enable
memories for the new ones. But I should
note that all of this only works if
you're a premium user. On the free
plans, you don't have projects. And once
again, memory management. I'll be
looking into how to properly port over
some of the old conversations to build
new memories. As of now, you can do it,
of course, but you can't be really sure
if they're being saved, as you just saw
in this little demo right here. Okay. In
this week's quick hits, the segment
where we just have a quick look at
multiple stories rather than actually
testing them or discussing them further.
We have a very colorful docket here.
Starting with Runway's game worlds.
Runway, the video generation company,
yet again looking for another way to use
their models for something productive.
In this case, it's the image generator.
And basically, it allows you to create
various worlds, which is yet another
take on these image generators. If
you're not a comic book designer or a
game designer, probably not relevant to
you, but I thought that was interesting.
But the next quick hit here might be
more relevant and useful to most viewers
of the show, and that's a Notebook LM
update, where now the video overviews
are available in over 80 languages, and
the audio overviews were upgraded to
even more languages, which is massive.
If you're not familiar, Notebook LM is
the app if you want hallucinationfree AI
usage that is just restricted to the
documents you give it, and it takes a
lot of documents. We have a great little
tutorial coming on the channel next
week, so make sure to subscribe so you
catch that one. It's like four minutes
and it covers the entire app with a
bunch of pro tips. And yeah, some of the
features now work in 80 languages, which
is impressive. Another quick story is
that Chetchd silently added the ability
to quiz yourself. And if you say quiz me
on Quinton Tarantino movies in quiz GPT,
by the way, this was a prompt of the
week in our weekly newsletter from this
week. So if you always want the newest
prompts and free apps that you can use
if you sign up there is our onwarding
sequence but after that it's just a
newsletter and yeah there we shared this
little prompt that you can now use too
and it creates this beautiful flashcards
right inside of chat is the view feature
reservoir dogs palm.com I think it was
fiction yeah the bride I mean that's
easy damn I'm kind of cracked at this
crystal fault there you go five out of
five one of my favorite directors
Hey, and that right there, ladies and
gentlemen, is essentially everything we
have for this week. I hope you found
something that was useful or
inspirational to yourself. My name is
Igor and I hope you have a wonderful